<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<document xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Nemerle Homepage</title>
  <section id="about">
    <title>About</title>
    <body>
      <p>
	<b>Nemerle</b> is a new programming language with the following
        planned features:
      </p>
      <ul>
	<li>Language with strong polymorphic typing compiled to CIL (.NET),
	    similar to OCaml</li>
	<li>Type inheritance and dynamic types introduced on demand which makes
            programming less error prone but still as easy as in scripting
	    languages</li>
	<li>Efficient integration of functional constructs with imperative
	    and object oriented code together with high level optimizations
	    that makes it possible to create efficient code with high level
	    language</li>
	<li>Easy to write syntax extensions that make programming easier
	    and facilitate the work on large projects</li>
	<li>Translation to and from TRS that gives support for integration
	    with automatic testing, program verification and profiling 
	    tools</li>
	<li>Compatibility with <b>CLI</b> (Common Language Infrastructure, part
	    of Microsoft's <b>.NET</b> framework) that gives access to a large
	    set of libraries, code written in other languages and it works on
	    different software platforms</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section id="download">
    <title>Download</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        At present the work on Nemerle is in early stages where we finish the
	first compiler of the core version of the language. The compiler is
	written in OCaml and will be used to bootstrap the full Nemerle
	compiler later. To compile it you need <a ref="http://www.ocaml.org/">
	OCaml 3.06</a> and to generate the documentation you need xsltproc
	and <a ref="http://www.kernel.pl/~malekith/xspp/">xspp</a>. All generated
        documentation is available from this site.
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Version of this page for offline browsing:
          <link>download/nemerle-web.tar.gz</link>.  It does not include
          compiler and documentation sources.
        </li>
        <li>
          Latest compiler and documentation source snapshot:
          <link>download/nemerle-latest.tar.gz</link>.
        </li>
        <li>
          Compiler and documentation source snapshots in
          <link>download/</link>.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section id="design">
    <title>Design</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        To meet our goals we divided our work into three parts:
      </p>
        <ul>
	<li>Core Nemerle compiler written in 
	    <a ref="http://www.ocaml.org">OCaml</a> that does not support some
	    of the features and generates C# code. It will be used to bootstrap
	    the full Nemerle compiler</li>
	<li>Nemerle compiler written in core Nemerle that will generate CIL or
	    generic CIL code and will have support for syntax extensions,
	    extended type inference, full code commenting convention and
	    documentation generation and well designed searchable and
	    extensible standard library</li>
	<li>Abstract Nemerle language generation for Nemerle compiler and back
	    translation from Abstract Nemerle to Nemerle. Translation between
	    Abstract Nemerle and Term Rewriting Systems and tools to facilitate
	    logical analysis of Nemerle code</li>
	</ul>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section id="docs">
    <title>Documents</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        At present we are finishing the core Nemerle compiler in OCaml and
	we have a description of the work we want to do in the next stages.
      </p>
      <p>Documents in suggested reading order:</p>
      <ul>
       <li>Core Nemerle:
        <ul>
        <li><a ref="coreNemDesc.html">Description of Core Nemerle</a></li>
        <li><a ref="coreNemGrammar.html">Grammar</a></li>
        <li><a ref="coreNemCompiler.html">Compiler</a> and description of
	    core Nemerle to C# translation</li>
        <!--
	<li><a ref="coreNemExamples.html">Examples</a></li>
        -->
        </ul>
       </li>
       <li>Nemerle <a ref="nemerlePlanned.html">planned features</a>
           description:
       </li>
       <li>Ideas about <a ref="TRSideas.html">translation to TRS</a>
           and formal reasoning tools.
       </li>
       <li><a ref="faq.html">FAQ</a></li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        We also have section about <a ref="absNem.html">our aims</a> to create formal semantics
        for Nemerle language, but it isn't any far.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section id="license">
    <title>License</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        The language implementation will be licensed under one of
	<a ref="http://www.opensource.org/">open source</a> licenses,
        probably BSD-like one.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section id="authors">
    <title>Authors and contact</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        The language is being worked on at the <a
        ref="http://www.ii.uni.wroc.pl/">Computer Science Institute</a>
        of <a ref="http://www.uni.wroc.pl/">University of Wroclaw</a> by
        <a ref="mailto:kaiser/at/tenet.pl">Lukasz Kaiser</a>,
        <a ref="http://www.kernel.pl/~malekith/">Michal Moskal</a> and
	<a ref="mailto:elessar/at/gdnmail.net">Andrzej Wasylkowski</a>.
      </p>
      <p>
        Any comments (especially constructive critique :-)) is welcomed.
	Please email us: <tt>nemerle/at/pld-linux.org</tt>
	(anti-spam: please change <tt>/at/</tt> to <tt>@</tt>).
      </p>
    </body>
    <subsection id="mailing-list">
      <title>Mailing list</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          There is mailing list setup at <a ref="http://pld-linux.org/">PLD
          Linux</a> mailing list server.  In order to subscribe please
          send empty email (subject and body are not important) to
          <tt>nemerle-subscribe/at/pld-linux.org</tt>, and reply to
          message sent by automaton there.  To post messages to the list,
          please use <tt>nemerle/at/pld-linux.org</tt>.
        </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </section>
</document>
